American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages. 1882-1958 Mss.497.3.B63c
American Philosophical Society
- Clallam
  - Clallam notes, 1917; AMs, 16L., 6p.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Vocabulary, especially nouns with diminutive and plural.
    Freeman and Smith 754
  - Notes on Clallam plural, ca.1900; Card file, 35 cards; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Notes on plural formations in Clallam.
    Freeman and Smith 756
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.6, reel 4
- Clatsop
  - Clatsop vocabulary, n.d., 1890?; AMs, 15L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Word list arranged alphabetically by the English.
    Freeman and Smith 757
- Cochiti
  - Cochiti texts with interlinear translations, n.d.; ca.1925-1940; TMs and AMs, 352L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In 4 parts. Texts with interlinear translations. Copies.
    Freeman and Smith 759
    Cf. Benedict (1931) for free translation of 20 texts.
  - Cochiti texts, word lists, and paradigms, 1921-1922; AMs, 5 notebooks [5-9]; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Pp. 479-1066 of original field notes. Texts [cf. copies in No. 759], word lists, paradigms, and shorthand notes.
    Freeman and Smith 760
    Cf. Benedict (1931).
- Coeur d'Alene
  - Coeur d'Alene Indian texts, ca. 1930?; TMs Cy, 418L.; Reichard, Gladys Amanda, 1893-1955
    Texts without translations, number I-LII (XVIII lacking). Accompanying note states that author has retained translation pending publication, after which this will be made available.
    Freeman and Smith 764
    Used for Reichard (1938)
  - Coeur d'Alene and Spokane vocabulary, 1908; AMs, 1 notebook; Teit, James Alexander, 1864-1922
    Words recorded on blanks provided in Powell (1877).
    Freeman and Smith 767
  - Coeur d'Alene vocabulary, ca. 1910; AMs, 17p.; Teit, James Alexander, 1864-1922
    Vocabulary items, relating to material culture and religion.
    Freeman and Smith 766
- Comox
  - Comox and Pentlatch texts, ca. 1910; AMs and TMs, 98L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    15 MS. texts with interlinear translation by Boas. Typescript of interlinear translation of 14 texts. 2 typed copies of interlinear translation. One additional text.
    Freeman and Smith 770
  - Comox-Satlolk materials, ca. 1890; AMs, 48p., 36L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In German and English. Includes vocabulary and text with German interlinear translation; Satlolk-English vocabulary.
    Freeman and Smith 771
    Cf. Boas (1895).
- Craho
  - Incomplete Kraho grammar, 1939; AMs, 254L.; Quain, Buell Halvor, 1912-1939
    Grammar prepared posthumously by Fannie Dunn Quain, ca. 1945, from notes of field work among Kraho on Tocantins River in Maranhao, Brazil. Contains material on phonetics, pronouns, verbs, syntax, 14 folkloristic texts, including some translation and notes.
    Freeman and Smith 775
    Donor, C. F. Voegelin, 1951.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 34
- Cree
  - Abstracts of Cree tales, ca. 1935; TMs with AMs additions, 75p.; Various authors
    A comparison of versions of Cree tales from the following sources: Skinner (1916); Teit (1921); Ahenakew (1929); Bloomfield (1930); and Bloomfield (1934).
    Freeman and Smith 776
  - Genealogical sketch of my family, 1948; AMs, 27p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Autobiography of Cree Indian, born at Atahkakoops Res. to Christian (Episcopalian) parents. A sickly lad, he studied medicine in 1918, giving it up to become head of mission on his reserve. Discusses his nineteenth century grandparents (grandfather and granduncles), their conversion, role among people. Mentions treaty of 1876, rebellion of 1885. Views his past from point of view of an acculturated Indian.
    Freeman and Smith 779
    Donor, Edward Ahenakew, grantee, 1948.
  - Tanning of leather, 1948; AMs, 8p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Discusses Cree methods of tanning. Images include pencil sketches of implements. Informants are James Moostoos, "who strangely enough admitted having done the female work of tanning some hides," and his wife, Susan. Letter of Ahenakew to Paul A. W. Wallace, June 10, 1948. Mentions Dr. William E. Lingelbach.Donor, Edward Ahenakew, grantee, 1948.
    Freeman and Smith 783
    Sketches.
  - Spirit help, 1948; AMs, 7p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Incidents of spirit contact reported by Indians, which Ahenakew, despite his Christian upbringing, believes in part. Drawings of conjuring tent and experiences of Chief Starblanket of Ahtahkakoop, who was also a Mitawiwin. Experience of magic and counter-magic in contest with another person having spirit help (participants were ancestral relatives of the author). Note to Dr. Paul A. W. Wallace, Nov. 12, 1948.
    Freeman and Smith 782
  - The We-tikoo, or He-who-is-alone, 1949; AMsS, 20p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Three documents discussing We-ti-koo (Windigo) possession, or cannibalism, among the Cree, as told by various informants, whom Ahenakew disbelieves. Two tales of family cannibalism told by Jerry Constant. Additional cases.
    Freeman and Smith 784
  - Non-human personalities, 1949; AMs, 10p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Tale told by Ahenakew's grandmother about Ma-Na-Kwa-Si-Wuk, a Cree-speaking "little people" who inhabit caves; also a personal narrative about Pa-Ha-Koos told by Sam Cook together with a description of a dance intended to pacify these game-controlling little creatures. Concludes with a narrative told by a relative who saw Pa-Ha-Koos even after becoming a Christian. Images include ink sketches of figures.
    Freeman and Smith 781
  - A-us-to-yit (Making a canoe ...), 1949; AMs and TMs, 8p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Techniques of manufacture described by informant Jerry Constant, age seventy-nine. Includes letter of Ahenakew to Dr. Paul A. W. Wallace, mentioning Cree and Blackfoot dictionaries. Added memo tells of informants used in No. 30 (65-08). Images include ink sketches.
    Freeman and Smith 777
  - Cree texts, "Series Two: Syllabary Texts from Sweet Grass Reserve", 1925; TMs, 683L.; Bloomfield, Leonard, 1887-1949
    Texts 47-113 plus appendix. Introduction by Bloomfield, texts written down by Harry Achenam. A sequel to Bloomfield (1934), but never published.
    Freeman and Smith 785
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 5-6
- Crow
  - Crow affixes, n.d.; AMs, 42L.; Lowie, Robert Harry, 1883-1957
    Arranged alphabetically by the Crow, apparently copied from texts and field notes.
    Freeman and Smith 814
    Cf. Lowie (1960) :385-392:
- Cuicateco
  - Brevisimas notas sobre el idioma Cuicateco, 1922; AMs Cy, 36L.; Angulo, Jaime de
    In Spanish. Grammatical sketch; 3 folkloristic 3 original narratives told by a Chiquihuitl n native.
    Freeman and Smith 818
- Dakota
  - Legends of the Oglala Sioux, 1937; TMs Cy, 70p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Copy of Rev. Luke C. Walker's collection of legends, ca. 1880, made by Ella Deloria from manuscript. The carbon copy bears reference numbers to questions of Miss Deloria in her field work verifying these legends
    Freeman and Smith 824
    Cf. No. 834
  - Dakota notes, 1932 -; TMs, 16L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Observations by Miss Deloria's brother of gestures, sleeping arrangements of full-blooded Dakotas
    Freeman and Smith 823
  - A Study of Osage consonant shifts, ca.1935?; TMs with MS. Additions, 68L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Teton, Yankton, and English. Comparisons of Dakota and Osage words. Ca. 1,074 pairs, together with discussion of sound correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by English. Yankton and Teton dialects of Dakota. Essay on consonant and vowel shifts
    Freeman and Smith 850
  - Dakota lexicon, ca. 1933; Card and slip file, 13 cards, 3 slips; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee and English. Examples of stem reduplication taken from Riggs (1890)
    Freeman and Smith 839
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 28
  - Dakota texts, n.d.; AMs and TMs, 55L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In Santee and English
    Freeman and Smith 831
    Texts with interlinear and free translations and notes; two in duplicate. Also a speech by V. V. Deloria recorded on phonograph
  - Miscellaneous Dakota notes, 1894 and later; AMs and TMs, 78L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In Teton, Santee, and English. Contains list of Dakota and other Siouian materials in Boas' files. Miscellaneous grammatical and lexicalnotes. Comparative word lists; Dakota-Winnebago; Ponca-Dakota; Mandan-Teton. Dakota word list; Dakota text. List of Teton dialect MSS. texts in Bureau of American Ethnology, comp.iled by George Bushotter (1887) and John Bruyier. Covering letter of J. Owen Dorsey, July 27, 1894
    Freeman and Smith 830
    Cf. no. 852 for copies of texts
  - Dakota autobiographies, ca. 1937; TMs with MS. Additions, 382L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Yankton, Santee, and English. Texts (II:1-11) with literal and free translations, and occasional ethnographic and linguistic notes
    Freeman and Smith 833
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 28-29
  - Dakota commentary on Walker's texts, 1937; TMs with MS. Additions, 47, 40L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee and English. Texts (VII:1-2) with literal and free translations and notes. Includes comments by two informants and itemized comments by the author with reference numbers to the c.c. of Walker Legends in No. 824. She finds linguistic and cultural inadequacies in both Introduction and Legends of Dr. Luke C. Walker
    Freeman and Smith 834
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 29
  - Dakota dictionary, 1935?; TMs, 2 notebooks; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Teton, Santee, and English. 1) A-m, na. 2) Ni-z. Ca. 5,000 Dakota lexical items with detailed English equivalents
    Freeman and Smith 835
  - Dakota ethnographic and conversational texts, 1937?; AMs and TMs, 220L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (VIII:1-10; V:4), with literal and free translations and detailed ethnographic and linguistic discussions.
    Freeman and Smith 836
  - Dakota games, n.d.; TMs, 35p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: text in Dakota with free English translation; grammatical notes
    Freeman and Smith 4197
  - A Dakota greeting, n.d.; TMs, 5p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: short text and translation in which the greeting involves saying the name of a dead person; discussion of the context and social acceptability of the naming; relating an incident in which naming a dead person was not considered appropriate; discussion of a short prayer said before drinking water
    Freeman and Smith 4198
  - Dakota informal texts and conversations, 1937?; TMs, 273L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (111:1-13), with literal and free translations, ethnographic and linguistic notes
    Freeman and Smith 838
  - Dakota play on words, n.d.; TMs, 19p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes text in Dakota with literal and free translations; grammatical notes
    Freeman and Smith 4199
  - A Dakota proverb, n.d.; TMs, 2p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: text with literal and free translations; discussion of prohibition against a man's traveling with/being alone with a woman not his wife and of aversion to open attempts by a woman to gain a man's attention
    Freeman and Smith 4200
  - Dakota speeches, 1937?; TMs, 77L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (V1:1-3) with literal and free translations and notes. Content generally relates to tribal factions dispute over New Deal Indian policy
    Freeman and Smith 841
  - Dakota tales, 1937; TMs, 105L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (IX:1-5) with literal and free translations and notes
    Freeman and Smith 843
  - Dakota texts from the Minnesota manuscript, 1839; 1941; TMs with MS. Additions, 45L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Forty-one ethnographic and folkloristic texts transcribed from manuscripts in the Minnesota Historical Society comp.iled by Gideon Pond and Samuel Pond. Teton versions added for comparison.
    Freeman and Smith 845
    Printed (Text 5, "The Skeptic"), Boas and Deloria (1941)
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 30
  - Dakota tales in colloquial style, 1937; TMs, with MS. Additions, 324L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (X:l, 3-5), with free translations and ethnographic and linguistic notes. Text no. 2 in this series is found in the carbon, copy 2
    Freeman and Smith 844
  - Dialect pun in Dakota, TMs, 9p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: text with literal and free translations; explanatory comments; grammatical notes
    Freeman and Smith 4201
  - Letters and miscellaneous materials in Dakota from the Minnesota manuscript., TMs, 70L; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee and English. Copies of letters and other materials in the Minnesota Historical Society; translations and grammatical notes by Ella Deloria. Contents: ***10 letters to Dr. Wm. [Williamson], Mr. R. [Stephen Riggs?], and R[enville?] from various Indians educated at the Mission school. Financial relations, Chippewa-Sioux warfare, religion, mission education, ethnography. ***appendix to 10th letter: a count or census of seven Dakota bands, total of 105 names, Aug. 15, 1838.***marginal comment on the count; texts of 3 songs.***an ethnographic text (Feb. 9, 1839) on hunting, warfare, and laws.***free translations of 1, 2, 3, and 4 above.***grammatical notes.
    Freeman and Smith 848
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 31
  - Old Dakota legends, n.d.; 1937?; TMs with MS. Additions, 358L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Texts (1:1-12), with literal and free translations and ethnographic and linguistic notes. Includes three year counts, one with illustrations
    Freeman and Smith 849
  - Special expressions in Dakota, TMs, 13p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: new expressions; odd words; sayings; jokes with literal and free translations; explanatory comments; grammatical notes
    Freeman and Smith 4202
  - Woodmen from Bear Creek, n.d.; TMs, 13p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Includes: illustration of some old traditions through the reported conversation in Dakota connected with the offer and acceptance of food and honoring the dead; English translations; discussions of the customs involved; notes on various Dakota words
    Freeman and Smith 4203
  - Dakota idioms, after 1932; TMs with MS. Additions, 64L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Contains idioms, with references to MS. tales. Idioms and similes, with references to MS. tales and a few references to Deloria (1932). A few editorial comments of Boas
    Freeman and Smith 837
  - Dakota song texts, 1937; TMs Cy, 180L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    Texts, corrected by Ella Deloria, with literal and free translations and notes. Collected from Densmore (1918), Burlin (1907), and unpublished collection of Yanktonai texts of George Herzog.
    Freeman and Smith 840
  - Dakota stems, grammatically treated, n.d.; ca. 1935; Slip file, ca. 800 slips; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Stem file, alphabetically arranged; with key
    Freeman and Smith 842
    Donor, Ernst P. Boas, 1946
  - Dakota word lists, grammatically selected and treated, ca. 1936; TMs and AMs, 554L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee, Teton, and English. Materials solicited by Boas from Miss Deloria: yellow slips contain questions and summaries by Boas; typed materials are replies of Miss Deloria. Arranged according to grammatical categories, Iapi Oaye, v. 65, no. 1, Jan. 1963, p. 1-4. Comparative listing of northwest coast specimens.
    Freeman and Smith 832
  - Dictionary materials in Dakota and related languages, ca. 1935; Slip file, 1,200 items; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In Santee and English. Handwritten slips by Boas; typewritten by Deloria. Reference numbers apparently to manuscript materials. Includes some related linguistic material
    Freeman and Smith 828
  - Legends in Santee Dakota, 1934; TMs, 139L., 148L.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Santee and English. 16 folkloristic texts and four historical narratives of the Lake Dwellers [Mdewakatuwa] covering events from 1800 to 1934 in sequence. Complete in vol. 1, an autobiographical narrative from Philip Robinson, born ca. 1860
    Freeman and Smith 847
  - Teton forms, entered in S. R. Riggs, A Dakota-English dictionary, 1890-1938?; AMs, 685p.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Teton and English. Teton forms entered in pencil of copy of S. R. Riggs (1890), a Santee dictionary
    Freeman and Smith 851
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 31-32
  - Teton myths, 1887-1888; 1937?; TMs with MS. illus.,; Deloria, Ella Cara
    In Teton and English. Typed copy of manuscript texts collected by George Bushotter, and John Bruyier, 1888, for James Owen Dorsey, now in Bureau of American Ethnology library. Folkloristic and ethnographic materials. 151 texts with literal and free translations and notes; 107 texts in free translation only. 2 texts of John Bruyier (Nos. 189, 224) and autobiography of George Bushotter (No. 101). Images include pencil and ink sketches of masks, war bonnet, toys, flutes, in Part II, version 2.
    Freeman and Smith 852
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 32-33
  - A phonemic analysis of a Dakota dialect, 1954; TMs, 13p.; Matthews, G. Hubert
    Based on the speech of one man whose parents were Yankton speakers and whose schoolmates were mostly Teton speakers
    Freeman and Smith 4205
- General
  - Bibliography on decorative art, 1890-1924; AMs, 150 slips; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Includes a general bibliography on anthropology. German, English, and Spanish sources.
    Freeman and Smith 1417
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 1
- Haida
  - Haida ethnography, 1893; TMs, 91L.; Deans, James
    Materials intended to accompany exhibit of Haida houses in the ethnography section of the World's Columbian Exposition, 1893. Contains "The Haida"; "Order [of] Haidah Houses as they used to stand in Skidegat's Town ..."; "How the Haida dispose of their dead" -- 2 versions. The first document bears emendations by Franz Boas.
    Freeman and Smith 1533
  - Haida lexicon, n.d.; AMs, ca. 150 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Disorganized slips from various MS. texts. Some have English equivalents
    Freeman and Smith 1537
  - Haida lexicon, n.d.; AMs, ca. 800 slips.; Unidentified
    Haida-English file.
    Freeman and Smith 1539
  - Notes on the composition of the verbal complex in Haida, n.d.; 1915?; AMs, 17L.; Haeberlin, Herman K.
    A critical reworking of a portion of Swanton (1911a).
    Freeman and Smith 1538
  - Haida texts, 1900-1902; TMs with AMs additions, 333 l.; Swanton, John Reed, 1873-1958
    Copies of texts obtained from Masset and Skidegat Haida, 1900-1902. Two texts have interlinear translation. Reference numbers refer to printed abstracts of Masset texts. Marginal comments by Franz Boas and Theresa M. Durlach.
    Freeman and Smith 1544
    Printed, Swanton (1908) and (1905b); abstracts in Swanton (1905a).
  - Haida texts, 1900-1901; TMs, with MS. additions. 350L.; Swanton, John Reed, 1873-1958
    Skidegat texts obtained in 1900-1901. Marginal page and line references refer to free translations in Swanton (1905b), probably made by Theresa M. Durlach, who cites these numbers in her work (1928).
    Freeman and Smith 1543
  - Haida grammatical notes and word list, 1900-1911; TMs and AMs, 127L.; Swanton, John Reed, 1873-1958
    English-Haida lexicon, ca. 1200 words; Haida-English lexicon, ca. 800 items. Also organized notes and word lists, a composite, based on 1900-1901 field work among Skidegat and Masset. Some work done by Theresa Durlach.
    Freeman and Smith 1542
  - Haida lexicon, n.d.; TMs and AMS, ca. 300 cards.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Lexicon, alphabetical by Haida, principally Masset dialect. Reference numbers refer to Swanton manuscripts and publications.
    Freeman and Smith 1540
- Hokan
  - Hokan-Siouan comparisons, 1917-1925; AMs, ca. 1300 cards and slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Comparisons among various families of the Hokan-Siouan phylum. Dividers separate sections as follows: Hokan-Siouan (Yuki; Moskogian: Caddoan; Siouan; Hokan-type Coahuiltecan-Butiaba); Washo-Hokan; Hokan-Coahuiltecan; Yana-Hokan. Subdivided by stems, grammatical categories, and occasionally by meaning.
    Much of the Yana-Hokan published in "The Position of Yana in the Hokan Stock," UCPAAE 13, 1 (1917).
    Freeman and Smith 1550
  - Hokan compared with various Middle and South American languages, 1924; AMs, 1L.; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960
    Word lists of 21 English items with equivalents in Yuman, Hokan, Subtiaba, Xinca, Lenca, Chibcha, Guayom, Chibchan, Zoque, Mixe; taken from published and unpublished sources.
    Freeman and Smith 1549
- Hopi
  - First report on Hopi, 1933; TMsS, 5L.; Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941
    Brief comment on phonemics, morphology, general and comparative remarks. Part of a letter to Edward Sapir.
    Freeman and Smith 1568
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 20
  - The Hopi language, n.d.; TMs cy, 59p.; Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941
    A grammatical sketch of the dialect of Mishongnovi pueblo.
    Freeman and Smith 4364
  - Hopi word list, 1915; AMs, 2 slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    21 items; Hopi with English equivalents.
    Freeman and Smith 1567
  - Hopi text, ca.1933-1941; AMs, 9L.; Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941
    Text on marriage customs with interlinear translation and grammatical notes.
    Freeman and Smith 1569
  - Hopi verb classes, Feb. 7, 1934; AMsS, 4L.; Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941
    Grammatical treatment.
    Freeman and Smith 1570
    Donor, Leslie Spier, 1957.
- Huastec
  - Vocabulario Wasteko, 1940; TMs Cy, 6L; McQuown, Norman A.
    In Spanish-Huastec. List of ca. 150 Huastec equivalents.
    Freeman and Smith 1582
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1950
- Huave
  - Huave-English dietionary, 1932-1952; AMs, 91L; Radin, Paul, 1883-1959
    In Huave-English and Spanish. A dictionary based on texts in Radin (1929b) and on the author's field work of 1912-1913. Additions were made from Milton and Clara Warkentin (1952) by the author some time after 1952. Film copy made before these revisions.
    Freeman and Smith 1588
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.5, reel 5
- Huichol
  - Huichol vocabulary, 1940; AMs, 3 l.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    In Spanish-Huichol. Vocabulary list of 125 items.
    Freeman and Smith 1601
- Hupa
  - Field notes in California Athabascan languages, 1902-1903; 1922; AMs, 18 notebooks.; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    Pome, Hupa, Kato, Wailaki, Sinkyone, Tolawa, and Nongatl texts, ethnographic and ethnohistoric materials.
    Freeman and Smith 1603
    Cf. Goddard (1903b) and (1923).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 42-43
  - Hupa text (South Fork of the Trinity), n.d.; 1901-1908; TMs Cy, 80L.; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    Interlinear text in duplicate, with free translation; another interlinear translated text in duplicate; a free translation of a third text.
    Freeman and Smith 1605
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 13
  - Hupa materials, 1903-1906; AMs, 11 notebooks and loose sheets.; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    Texts, translations, historical accounts, paradigms, vocabulary lists, grammatical notes, ethnological notes. Some Wailaki text material included
    Freeman and Smith 1604
    CfC: Goddard (1903b), (1904), (1905).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 43
  - Hupa texts and slipfile, 1927; AMs, 11 notebooks of ca. 125 p. each; ca. 5,000 slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Hupa texts with English translation. Slip file is vocabulary with grammatical notes filed alphabetically Hupa-English.
    Freeman and Smith 4369
    1607
  - Hupa Indians, 1923; TMs with Ms, illus., 11 folders; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    In Hupa and English. Typed copied of manuscript texts of notes on myths; doctors and medicine; birth, puberty, marriage and death; omens; material culture; villages and houses; names; cosmography and geography; warfare. Images include a map of Humboldt County, California and pencil sketches of decorative patterns.